Each year, we look forward
to the high-quality video presentations
毎年の地区大会で
私たちは素晴らしいビデオを
楽しんでいます
that have become
a highlight of our conventions.
Work is underway
on videos and dramas for future conventions.
今もドラマを含む
さまざまなビデオが制作中です
The set construction
「イエスが伝えた良い知らせ」で
使われるセットや他の必要な物の制作も
and other work needed for the series
The Good News According to Jesus
順調に進んでいます
is well along.
Additionally, planning and construction
of our new media production facility
ビデオやオーディオを制作する
米国の新しい施設の計画や建設も
in the United States
is moving ahead steadily.
着実に進んでいます
All of these efforts
are supported by voluntary donations.
こうした活動は自発的な寄付によって
支えられています
If you would like to have a share
エホバの証人の世界的活動を
サポートしたいと思われますか
in supporting the worldwide work
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
one way you can do so
そうする方法の1つは
寄付を行うことです
is through your financial contributions.
For more information,
詳しくは donate.jw.orgを
ご覧ください
please visit donate.jw.org.
We have seen
エホバは私たちに 幸せで
that Jehovah promises us a future
平和な将来が来ると約束しています
filled with happiness and peace.
How will universal peace come about,
誰もがエホバに仕え 平和になる時は
and what will it mean for mankind?
どのように訪れるのでしょうか
Please pay close attention
to Brother Geoffrey Jackson,
統治体の
ジェフリー･ジャクソン兄弟の話に
a member of the Governing Body,
よく耳を傾けてください
as he answers those questions
in the final talk of this convention,
この地区大会の最後の話です
主題は 「誰もがエホバに仕え
平和になる時が来る！」
entitled “Universal Peace Is Sure to Come!”
What is true peace?
平和とは何でしょうか
For those who live in lands
where they have wars,
戦争が起きている地域に
住む人たちにとって
no doubt the focus they have on true peace
平和という言葉で最初に
思い浮かべるのは
戦争が終わって戦いや紛争が
全くない状態になることでしょう
is to stop fighting, to stop the conflicts,
to not have any wars.
And it’s true that peace
does include an absence of war.
戦争があれば平和とは
言えないというのは事実です
But in many cases, the efforts of mankind
でもたいてい 戦争を終わらせて平和を
達成しようとする人間の取り組みは
to try and gain peace by stopping wars
is similar to what we say
is a Band-Aid solution.
いわばバンドエイドを
貼るような解決策です
どういうことでしょうか
What do we mean by that?
Well, a person may have a horrible sore,
皮膚にひどい傷があるとします
がんの可能性もあります
perhaps even cancerous.
And if he just puts a Band-Aid over the top,
その上にバンドエイドを貼っただけでは
傷は隠せるかもしれませんが
maybe it hides the sore,
本当の解決にはならない
のではないでしょうか
but it really doesn’t solve the problem
—does it?—
平和とは単に戦争を終わらせる
ということではありません
because peace is not just an end of war.
考えてみてください
戦争がない国に住んでいたとしても
You know yourself, if you were to live
in a country where there isn’t any war
but you’re still worried about your health,
健康や安全について
心配なことがあったり
your well-being, and your safety
食べる物に困っていたり
or if you feel sick and hungry,
病気になったりしたら
平和な生活を送っている
と言うでしょうか
would you say that you’re having
a peaceful life?
Of course not.
言わないでしょう
According to the Bible, the word “peace”
聖書によれば 「平和」という言葉は
戦争がないよりはるかに
多くのことを意味しています
means far more than just an absence of war.
It means good health, well-being, and safety.
健康や安全や安心も意味しています
And from our convention, we’ve seen
この大会で平和にいろいろなことが
関係することを学びました
that there’s a lot involved with true peace.
It includes having
a peaceful relationship with Jehovah God.
平和な関係 まずエホバ神との
そして周りの人との
平和な関係が含まれます
It also means having
a peaceful relationship with others.
And also it includes
さらに 内面の平和を得て
the peace of heart and mind
that gives us tranquility.
穏やかな気持ちで
いられることも含まれます
でも この最後の話で考えるのは
But now in this final talk,
we’re going to consider a bigger issue,
もっと大きなことです
and that is universal peace.
それは全ての平和です
Now, what do we mean by universal peace?
全ての平和とはどういうことでしょうか
ここで考える全ての平和とは
What we mean by universal peace
is a type of peace
天と地のあらゆる場所で
that is everywhere in heaven and on earth
あらゆる面で見られる平和です
平和でない所はどこにもありません
—in all aspects of life.
It’s the type of peace that only the God
of peace, Jehovah, can bring
それは 平和の神エホバだけが
「平和の統治者」イエス・キリストを
用いてもたらすことのできる平和です
along with the “Prince of Peace,”
Jesus Christ.
間もなく エホバとイエスは
Soon they will take dramatic steps
再び全てを平和にするために
驚くべきことをします
toward the restoration of universal peace.
Let’s take our Bibles,
and if we turn together
聖書を開いて ローマ 16:20を
ご一緒に読みましょう
to Romans 16:20,
we’ll see what’s included
再び全てが平和になるには
in this restoration of universal peace
何が起きる必要があるか見てみましょう
ローマ 16:20です
—that’s Romans 16:20.
こうあります
「平和を与える神により
There we’re told: “For his part,
“the God who gives peace will crush Satan
間もなくサタンは皆さんの
足の下で砕かれます
“under your feet shortly.
私たちの主イエスの惜しみない
親切が皆さんに示されますように」
May the undeserved kindness
of our Lord Jesus be with you.”
この聖句から分かるように
再び全てが平和になるには
Yes, the restoration of universal peace
also includes
悪魔サタンが砕かれなければなりません
the crushing of Satan the Devil.
この大会の最後であるこの話では
So in our final discussion,
the final talk of this convention,
これから主に次の4つの点を考えます
we’re going to consider four basic questions.
The first one is,
1つ目 全てが平和な状態が
失われたのはいつか
When was universal peace disturbed?
2つ目 再び全てを平和にするのは誰か
Second, Who will restore universal peace?
3つ目 それはどのように行われるか
The third question, How will it be restored?
And then finally, we’re going to think
about what further blessings
そして最後に 人類がさらに
どんな祝福を得られるか
について考えます
mankind will enjoy at that time.
でも こうした点について
考えていく前に
But before we go on
to answer those questions,
大会で学んだ点をご一緒に
振り返ってみましょう
let’s review together
the program that we’ve had.
素晴らしい大会だったと
感じておられるに違いありません
I’m sure you’ll agree that this has been
a beautiful convention.
ぜひ平和をつくりたいという
気持ちになりました
And it’s encouraged us to pursue peace.
But what are some of the good points
that you remember from the program?
皆さんは特にどんな点が
良かったと思われましたか
Well, as we mentioned already, there are
three aspects to peace that we’ll discuss.
先ほど述べたように平和には
3つの面がありましたが
1つ目はエホバ神との平和でした
First of all, our peace with Jehovah God.
The Friday program finished
with the final talk,
1日目のプログラムの最後の話では
偽物の平和に惑わされないように
注意しなければならないという
and that’s where it mentions
about not being misled
大切な点が強調されました
by imitation peace.
And then Sunday,
what a beautiful public discourse we had!
3日目には「神と友達になるには」
という主題の
It said “Friendship With God—How Possible?”
素晴らしい公開講演を聞きました
And then the second aspect of our peace
平和の別の面として考えたのは
ほかの人との平和でした
is peace with one another.
The first day, remember,
we had that beautiful symposium
1日目に「家庭の平和に
欠かせないもの」という
シンポジウムがありました
on family peace.
What were some of the things
that we need to do
家庭の平和のためにどんなことを
する必要があったでしょうか
to have peace in our family?
Well, love and respect are important.
愛と敬意が大切でした
良いコミュニケーションや
みんなで協力すること
We need to improve
our communication with one another.
一緒にエホバに仕えることが必要でした
We need to work as a team
and worship together.
And then Saturday, we had
another interesting symposium
2日目に「平和を壊すものを
『脱ぎ捨てる』」という主題の
on what it said about peace wreckers,
興味深いシンポジウムがありました
things that can wreck peace.
平和を壊すものには
どんなものがありましたか
Do you remember some of those?
シンポジウムでは 自慢 ねたみ
Inappropriate boasting,
envy, dishonesty, harmful gossip,
不正直 悪いうわさ話
怒りが取り上げられました
and uncontrolled anger.
3つ目は個人の平和
And then the third aspect of peace
deals with our personal peace,
試練に遭っても穏やかな気持ちで
いられる内面の平和です
our inner calm despite trials.
2日目に 平和という絆を
守ることについて
On Saturday, we had a very interesting talk
that mentioned the need
to safeguard our bond of peace.
とても興味深い話がありました
And then on Sunday, we went through
another symposium where it gave examples
3日目には 平和をまいて平和を
刈り取った人たちの手本を取り上げた
of those who had sowed peace
and then reaped peace.
シンポジウムを楽しむことができました
プログラムに目を通すと
As we look through the program,
I’m sure there are so many points
大会で学んだいろいろな点を
思い出しますね
that you can remember that you enjoyed.
そして どの大会でもバプテスマが
Of course, one of the highlights
at any convention
ハイライトの1つです
is when we have the baptism.
この大会でバプテスマを受けた皆さんを
If you were baptized at this convention,
we’d like to welcome you!
心から歓迎いたします
Yes, we welcome you
to the Christian brotherhood
皆さんは愛する兄弟姉妹です
because we know that you’re working hard
to have peace with Jehovah God.
エホバ神との平和な関係を持つため
一生懸命努力しておられます
ではここでビデオを見ましょう
But now at this point, let’s watch a video
この大会でいろいろな
ビデオを見ましたが
that gives us some lessons
with regard to what we saw
そこから学んだ幾つかの点を
振り返ることができます
in the various videos in this convention.
ご覧ください
Enjoy!
ねえみんな ブルックだよ
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
Guess who just walked in?
来た来た 誰だと思う？
オリビアです
Olivia.
で ジェイク
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
And there’s Jake.
Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
しないでしょ 超真面目だもん
自分ではどうにも
できないように思うよね
It feels out of your control, doesn’t it?
Remember when we studied
about the Shulammite girl?
シュラムの乙女について勉強したの
覚えてる？
Who was really in control?
彼女は圧力に負けちゃったかしら？
負けなかった
She was.
あなたも同じように強くなれるわよ
You have the same power.
そう思っていれば
気持ちを強く持って行動できるわね
If you believe that,
it’ll change how you handle the pressure.
正しいことをしていれば
平和な気持ちでいられる
My peace comes from doing the right thing.
“I am a wall.”
「私は城壁」
臆病者！こんなもん ごみだ
You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
牢番がパウロにした仕打ちを考えて
Think about what the jailer had done to Paul.
牢番を憎んでも仕方がなかったよね
He could have hated him for it.
Yeah, he could have.
うん でもそうしなかった
But I guess he saw the jailer’s pain
instead of just his own.
きっと 自分のことより
牢番の気持ちを考えたんだと思う
1つだけ見ていただけますか
Let me show you just one scripture.
All right, one scripture.
1つだけな
Jehovah has taught us to love,
エホバはいつも
愛を示すことを教えてくれた
and he’s given our family
それに 家族に欠かせないものをくれた
peace.
それは平和
皆さんこんにちは
デミュアデザインのヘイリーです
Hello, everyone.
Haley from DeNure Design here.
You don’t think she’s showing off?
やり過ぎだと思いません？
Is this just about Haley?
ヘイリーが悪いってこと？
ちょっとこれ見てよ
Can you believe her?
全部を見たわけじゃないけど
I haven’t seen all her posts.
If Celia agrees that Haley
is doing something she shouldn’t,
セリア姉妹がそんなふうに
言ってるんだったら
you should talk to her.
ヘイリーと話した方がいいよ
I’ve noticed
この間上げてた投稿のことなんだけど
your posts lately on QuicPost.
それが何？
What about them?
自慢してると思われてるみたいよ
Some people might think you’re bragging.
誰が言ってるの？エミリーでしょう？
Who would think like that?
You?
そんなに怒らないで ジェイクが・・・
I didn’t want to upset you.
Jake said that I needed to take . . .
ジェイクも！みんなが私のこと
良くないって言ってるの？
Jake! So everyone thinks
my posts are inappropriate?
そういうことじゃなくって
That’s not what I am saying at all.
You are such . . .
そういうとこ あるよね
Think back to a time
自分が許してもらいたいと
思った時のこと 思い出してみて
when you wanted forgiveness.
「愛は辛抱強く 親切」
“Love is patient and kind.”
愛は嫉妬しない
It’s not jealous.
I’m sorry, Haley.
ごめんヘイリー
平和を壊さない鍵は 心からの愛です
Genuine affection fights peace wreckers.
And affection grows when we really know
兄弟姉妹のことをよく知れば
愛は強くなります
our brothers and sisters well.
I was always impressed
2人は本当にいつも仲がいいですよね
with how close you two were.
Well, it wasn’t always that way.
でも そうじゃないときもあった
No.
うん ささいなことから口論になった
What started as a small disagreement
just exploded.
引っ張ってるのは兄さんだろ！
You!
You’re the problem.
I needed a lot of help from Jehovah
エホバの助けがどうしても必要だった
to make things right with Nick.
ニックと仲直りするために
There was a misunderstanding
ちょっとした誤解があって
that got blown all out of proportion.
それが大きな問題になっちゃったんです
And I didn’t handle it the best.
私の対応も良くなかった
平和に仲良くやっていくことが
試されたんですよ
That’s when our peace
was really put to the test.
長老団は全員一致で
資格がないと決めたんだ
The body decided, unanimously,
that he should no longer serve.
カールが圧力をかけたから
じゃないですか！
Because you pushed them!
フィルは知らなかったんですが
Phil didn’t know just how tense things were
between Tim and I.
ティムとの関係が
険悪になっちゃったんです
エホバに忠実に仕え続けた
聖書中の人たちの例を調べた
I found comfort
in accounts of Jehovah’s servants.
They helped me realize that
気付かされた 兄弟たちとの平和は
being at peace with my brothers
was more important
than any appointed position.
どんな立場で奉仕するか
ということより重要なんです
It wasn’t easy,
簡単ではなかったけど
but we talked it out.
きちんと話し合った
エホバの助けで仲直りできた
And we were able to make peace
with Jehovah’s help.
Without peace,
平和がなかったら その後の変化に
対応できたかどうか分からない
I don’t know how we could’ve managed
what was to come.
裁判で 刑務所に入れられるという
判決が言い渡された時
At that moment when you hear the verdict
that you’ll stay in prison,
まるで顔面を殴られて
意識が遠のくような感覚で
it’s like you’ve been knocked unconscious.
頭の中が真っ白になりました
But then
the doors of the elevator opened up,
でも エレベーターのドアが開いて
and in front of us . . .
目に飛び込んできたのは
That’s Jehovah.
エホバのおかげです
もう駄目だと思った時 エホバは
私たちを元気づけるために
When you’re just about to lose
all your strength,
Jehovah does that something for you.
必ず何かをしてくれるんです
ロシアの兄弟姉妹についての記事です
The Russian brothers and sisters,
I pray for them constantly
兄弟たちはとても大変な状況にいます
because they are going
through a very tough time.
それで 兄弟姉妹のことを
いつも祈っています
平和は周囲の状況
What I’ve learned from all of this
起きていること
is peace isn’t from what’s outside,
経験していることから来るのではない
ということが分かりました
from what’s going on,
or from what you’re experiencing.
I’ve learned that peace is on the inside,
平和とは内面の状態のことで それは
and that comes from Jehovah.
エホバから来るんです
とても大切なことを学びました
What priceless lessons those were!
But now, at this point, friends,
we’re going to turn our attention
ではこれから 全ての平和という
大きなことについて
to that bigger issue
—universal peace.
順番に考えていきましょう
全てが平和な状態が失われたのはいつか
Remember the first question
we’re going to answer?
When was universal peace disturbed?
これが1つ目に考える点です
Before mankind was created,
人間が創造されるより前
計り知れないほど長い間
全てが平和でした
universal peace existed for countless ages.
It was just like a beautiful pond of water
それはまるで鏡のように
波一つない美しい水面のようでした
that was undisturbed
—no ripples, mirrorlike in appearance.
何にも乱されることなく
In other words, there was
utmost harmony with Jehovah
エホバと全ての天使たちの間に
完全な一致が見られていました
and with all the spirit creatures.
But then it’s just as if a rock was thrown
ところが美しい水面に石が
投げ込まれたかのように
into that beautiful pond
and peace started to be disturbed.
平和が乱され始めました
When do you think that happened?
それはいつのことでしょうか
Well, we’ll find the answer to that question
by turning to the Bible,
その質問の答えを
聖書から見てみましょう
どうぞヨハネ第一 3:8を
お開きください
and this time, if we look at 1 John 3:8
—that’s 1 John 3:8—
ヨハネ第一 3:8です
notice the answer to the question,
When did the problem start?
問題が始まったのはいつか
その答えを見つけてください
There we’re told: “The one who practices sin
こうあります
「罪を犯し続ける人は
“originates with the Devil,
悪魔から出ています
“because the Devil has been sinning
from the beginning.
悪魔は初めから罪を犯してきたからです
“For this purpose the Son of God
was made manifest,
神の子が現れたのは
悪魔の行いを終わらせるためです」
to break up the works of the Devil.”
So notice the answer to the question.
問題が始まったのはいつですか
“Because the Devil has been sinning
from the beginning,”
「悪魔は初めから罪を犯して
きたからです」とありました
or, as the footnote says,
‘from the time that he began.’
初めとはいつでしょうか
Does that mean right from the very time
when he was created?
創造された初めから悪魔だった
ということでしょうか
No, he wasn’t the Devil then, was he?
いいえ その時は悪魔ではなくて
He was a perfect angel.
完全な天使でした
So when was it
では 全てが平和な状態が乱され
始めたのはいつだったでしょうか
that this universal peace
started to be disturbed?
美しい水面に波が立ち始めたのは
いつでしょうか
When was it that the ripples
started to go through the universe?
Well, you might remember
それは ご存じかもしれませんが
that it wasn’t at the time
that he deceived Eve.
悪魔がエバを欺いた時では
ありませんでした
It’s a little bit like when the Bible says
a woman gives birth to a child,
ちょっと考えてみてください
子供の命が始まるのは
that’s not when the child’s life starts,
is it?
母親が出産する時ではありません
もっと前に始まります
It starts well before then.
So likewise, this disruption
of the universal peace
同じように 全てが平和な状態が
乱され始めたのは
began in heaven first,
まず天でのことでした
at the time that the angel who became Satan
それはサタンになった天使が
崇拝されたいと思って
started to covet the position of Jehovah
エホバの立場を欲しがり
始めた時のことです
to want worship from others.
And by doing this,
he alienated himself from God
そのようにしてその天使は神から離れ
もはやエホバの意志に
沿わない者になりました
and no longer was he in harmony
with Jehovah’s will.
Then that sinful attitude
そして エデンの園で
その罪深い傾向が表面化しました
was manifested in the garden of Eden.
That’s when he took the next step
さらに一歩進んで
and started to disturb the peace
of Adam and Eve
アダムとエバの平和を乱し始めたのです
and, of course,
they lost their peace with God.
2人は神との平和を失いました
But let’s take a moment and think
ではここで エデンの園での出来事に
about what was really involved
実際のところ何が関係していたのかを
少し考えてみましょう
with those events
there in the garden of Eden.
Some very important issues were raised.
その時 とても重要なことが
問題にされました
Remember how Satan, first of all,
spoke to Eve?
サタンがまずエバに何と言ったか
覚えていますか
He asked what seemed
like a ridiculous question: ‘Is it true
ばかげた質問に思えることを尋ねました
「どの木の実を食べるのも神が許して
くれないというのは本当ですか
‘that God hasn’t allowed you to eat
from any tree in the garden?
全部駄目なんですか」
All the trees are banned?’
もちろんそんなことはありませんでした
Well, of course, that’s ridiculous.
何をしたかったんでしょうか
But what was he doing?
He was calling into question
Jehovah’s qualities.
エホバが善い方であることに
疑いを抱かせようとしていました
Yes, he was inferring
that Jehovah may not be so generous.
エホバは良いものを与えてくれない
けちな神なんじゃないか
Maybe he’s stingy.
アダムとエバに権利があるものを
与えていないんじゃないか と
Perhaps he’s holding things back
from Adam and Eve
ほのめかしていたのです
that they really should have.
And then Satan went one step further.
それからサタンはもう一歩進んで
こう言います
He said: “You . . . will not die.”
「あなたたちは⋯⋯死にません」
Really what he was saying is,
‘Jehovah is a liar.’
「エホバはうそつきだ」と
言っていたようなものです
What a horrible accusation!
あまりにひどい話です
Sadly, Eve didn’t defend Jehovah.
でも エバはエホバを
擁護しませんでした
We would have expected
that she would have said to Satan:
本来ならサタンにこう答えるはずです
‘Who are you? I don’t know you.
「あなたは誰ですか あなたのことは
知らないので信じられません
‘Why would I believe you?
愛のある天のお父さんのことは
知っています」
I know my loving heavenly Father, Jehovah.’
But no, she sided with the Devil.
でも エバはサタンの側を選びました
So, what would Jehovah do?
エホバはどうするでしょうか
Well, think for a moment about this:
ちょっと考えてみてください
What if someone accused you wrongly
in front of everybody,
誰かがみんなの前で
あなたのことを根拠もなく非難し
calling you a liar,
saying all sorts of bad things about you?
うそつき呼ばわりし あなたについて
いろいろ悪いことを言います
What would you do?
どうしますか
Would you go and punch them in the face?
その人にパンチを食らわせますか
Well, if you did, that wouldn’t be
the right thing to do
そんなことをするのはよくありませんし
and it certainly wouldn’t answer
the questions raised.
問題となっている点を
解決することにもなりません
You see, was that person really true
in what they said or not?
その人の言ったことが
正しいかどうかが問題です
How would you probably solve this?
どのように解決するでしょうか
Well, you might take the person to court.
裁判に訴えるかもしれません
And in that court case, that person
その人は裁判で あなたが
うそつきであることを示すために
could offer whatever evidence they feel
they have to prove that you’re a liar.
自由に証拠を提出することができます
On the other hand,
you can produce witnesses to prove
一方 あなたは自分がうそつきではなく
正直な人間であることを示すために
that really you aren’t a liar,
but you’re very truthful.
証人を立てることができます
And then finally, there would be
a decision made
最終的に 誰が正しく誰が
間違っているか判決が下されます
as to who was right and who was wrong.
Well, in a similar way,
それと同じように
these issues (these questions)
raised in the garden of Eden
エデンの園で提起された問題によって
いわば裁判が始まりました
started a symbolic court case.
So how did Jehovah respond?
知恵のあるエホバは
Wisely, he allowed time
その問題を解決するために
時間をかけることにしました
to settle these issues.
He allowed Satan the opportunity
サタンに人類を支配して
自分の方法で物事を行うことを
一時的に許しました
to try and rule mankind to do things his way.
At the same time, mercifully,
he provided the hope
また 憐れみ深い神は
アダムとエバのまだ生まれていない
子孫が希望を持てるようにしました
for the unborn children of Adam and Eve.
You remember at Genesis 3:15,
ご存じのように 創世記 3:15は
it speaks of an “offspring,” or a Son,
who’d come later
「子孫」について述べています
その子孫は後に現れ
and eventually undo the bad
サタンが最初に行った悪いことの
影響をやがて除き去り
that Satan had done there in the beginning
and eventually free mankind
from sin and death.
人類を罪と死から自由にします
But what has Satan been doing
でもサタンは機会を与えられて以来
どんなことを行っているでしょうか
since this opportunity has been given to him?
He’s still craving worship from other people.
今でも人々からの崇拝
人々が自分を神と認めて
ひれ伏すことを強く望んでいます
He wants them to bow down to him
and acknowledge him as their god.
He also uses lies and deceit
さらに うそや偽りを使って
人々の「思考を遮［って］」います
to ‘blind the minds’ of persons.
And he also has great anger,
particularly at this time in history,
大きな怒りを抱いています
自分の終わりが近いことを
知っている今は特にそうです
where he knows his end is near.
And so he’s influencing the world to hate
サタンは世の中の人々に影響を及ぼし
anyone who stands up on Jehovah’s side.
エホバの側に付く人に対する
憎しみをあおっています
But now, let’s think
about a very interesting question:
ここでちょっと次の点を
考えてみましょう
Even though we’re living
私たちがサタンの支配する
世界で生活していながら
in a world that is ruled by Satan,
is it possible at all
神との平和を持つことなど
可能かという点です
for us to have a measure of peace with God?
We’re experiencing
so many trials and challenges.
今は試練や問題がたくさんあります
We face opposition.
反対 病気 経済上の問題
災害に直面します
We have illness, economic problems,
disasters.
Is it possible to have some measure of peace?
そんな中で幾らかでも平和を
持つことは可能でしょうか
The answer is found again in the Scriptures,
答えはやはり聖書にあります
and this time, if you turn with me, please,
今度はコリント第二の手紙の
1章をどうぞお開きください
to the book of 2 Corinthians chapter 1
コリント第二 1:3, 4を読みます
—Second Corinthians 1:3, 4—
notice this beautiful promise:
素晴らしい約束が書かれています
“Praised be the God and Father
of our Lord Jesus Christ,
「私たちの主イエス・キリストの
父である神が賛美されますように
“the Father of tender mercies
神は 温かな憐れみの父
“and the God of all comfort,
あらゆる慰めの神であり
“who comforts us in all our trials
私たちがどんな試練に遭うとしても
慰めてくださいます
“so that we may be able to comfort others
in any sort of trial
それで私たちは 神からの慰めにより
どんな試練に遭う人をも
慰めることができます」
with the comfort that we receive from God.”
Isn’t that a beautiful scripture?
本当にいい聖句ですね
What does it highlight?
この聖句から分かるように
Notice, Jehovah obviously is aware
of our suffering.
エホバは私たちの苦しみに
気付いておられます
He feels for us.
He wants to help us.
思いやってくださいます
助けたいと思っています
It mentions he’s
“the Father of tender mercies.”
「温かな憐れみの父」なのです
But at the same time, we realize
でもだからといって
現時点で私たちの問題全てを
解決されるわけではありません
that Jehovah won’t step in
and fix all our problems at this point.
Why?
Because this is the time that Satan
なぜなら 今はサタンが
機会を与えられて
has the opportunity
to try and rule the world,
世界を支配している時だからです
and the problems of this world
really come from Satan.
世の中の問題の原因は
サタンにあるということです
At the same time,
we wouldn’t expect Jehovah to step in
それで エホバが悪魔サタンを
助けるかのように
and start to solve the problems
as if he were helping Satan the Devil.
問題を解決することを
私たちは期待したりはしません
But there is a time
when Satan will be taken away
でもやがて サタンが除き去られて
問題が解決される時が来ます
and the problems will be solved.
We could think of Jehovah’s position
as similar to that of a father
エホバの立場を例えてみましょう
ある父親がマラソンに参加している
息子を見守っています
whose son is running in a marathon race.
As he sees his son running in the race,
走っている息子の様子を見ていると
he may see his son is starting to tire out.
かなり疲れてきているのが分かります
Well, perhaps you may see that others
in the race are not obeying the rules.
ほかのランナーがルールを守って
いないことにも気付きます
Does that mean that the father then jumps in
and takes the place of his son
では 父親はコースに侵入して
息子の代わりに走ったり
and helps him as he runs along?
息子を手助けしたりするでしょうか
No, the rules don’t allow it.
いいえ それはルール違反です
But what the father can do
is continue to encourage his son:
父親にできるのは声援を
送り続けることです
“Keep on going.
Yes, you can do it!”
「諦めちゃ駄目！よくやってる！」
So in a similar way,
what does this verse tell us?
それと同じようにこの聖句は
何と言っているでしょうか
It said that Jehovah gives us comfort.
エホバが慰めを与えてくださる
と言っています
How does he do that?
どのようにでしょうか
He gives us peace
by means of his Word, the Bible;
聖書によって 聖なる力によって
愛情深い兄弟姉妹によって
by means of holy spirit;
and by the loving brotherhood that we have.
エホバは平和を与えてくださいます
So at this point, what we’d like to do
is have a look at a video that will highlight
ではここで ご一緒に
ビデオを見ましょう
大変な時にもエホバがどのように
助けてくださるか注目してください
how Jehovah lovingly helps us
even in times of need.
We are living
私たちが生きているのは
in “critical times
「困難で危機的な時」です
hard to deal with.”
Many people have lost all hope,
多くの人は 未来に希望を持てません
and servants of Jehovah
エホバに仕える人たちも試練に遭います
are not free from trials.
We may face loss of property,
家や持ち物を失ったり
loss of health,
病気になったり
loss of loved ones.
家族を亡くしたりします
We may experience deep emotional trauma
耐え難いほど悲しい出来事を経験したり
信仰のために
投獄されたりすることもあります
or even imprisonment for our faith.
Our trials are similar to those of Job,
エホバに忠実に仕えたヨブも
同じような経験をしました
a faithful servant of Jehovah
悲しみのあまり「なぜ私は生まれた時に
死ななかったのだろう」と言いました
who was so saddened that he once asked,
‘Why didn’t I die at birth?’
私たちも そういう気持ちに
なったことがあるかもしれません
Perhaps we’ve had moments like that.
But why should we not lose hope?
でも 希望をなくさないでください
Because with every trial
comes Jehovah’s support
どんな試練に遭っても
エホバのサポートがあるからです
—support received in many forms:
どんな面でのサポートがあるでしょうか
material support,
生活の面で
emotional support,
感情の面で
信仰の面で
and spiritual support.
And while Jehovah
エホバは今全ての試練を
なくすわけではありませんが
will not remove all our trials now,
we trust that with his support,
エホバが支えてくださるので
耐えることができます
we can endure them
新しい世界では
つらいことがなくなるのです
until they disappear
in “the real life” to come.
詩編 34:17,18には
こうあります
Psalm 34:17, 18 says:
“They cried out, and Jehovah heard . . .
「正しい人が叫ぶと
エホバは聞いてくださった⋯⋯
He saves those who are crushed in spirit.”
打ちのめされた人を
救ってくださる」
So we can see that even though
our peace has been disturbed,
たとえ平和が脅かされるとしても
神との平和を持てることが分かります
we can enjoy peace with God.
So let’s think about our second question.
では 2つ目の点を考えましょう
Remember, that question was,
どんな点でしたか
Who will restore universal peace?
再び全てを平和にするのは誰かです
Well, we already saw the answer
聖書の最初の預言である
創世記 3:15に触れた時に
when we referred to Genesis 3:15,
もう答えを言いましたね
the first prophecy in the Bible.
その聖句は約束の子孫について
述べていました
It mentioned the promised offspring, or Son,
and that one is Jesus Christ
—the Prince of Peace.
それはイエス・キリスト
平和の統治者です
He has the key role
イエスは再び全てを平和にする上で
in restoring universal peace.
大きな役割を果たします
Very soon,
間もなく イエスは今の世界を除き去る
という決定的な行動を取り
he’s going to take the decisive action
to remove this old world
and then take progressive steps
それから着実に物事を進め
toward the restoration of universal peace.
再び全てを平和にします
But why can we be so sure
では イエスが間もなく行動すると
確信できるのはなぜですか
that Jesus will come soon?
It’s a very simple answer
答えは明らかです
—by seeing the current events
that are happening in the world today.
いま世界で起きていることを
見れば確信できます
Yes, as we look around us,
世界の出来事を見ると分かりますが
we see so many things that are happening
いま私たちの周りで起きている
さまざまな事柄は
that proves to us
イエスが間もなく助けてくださることを
はっきり示しています
that Jesus will soon step in to help us.
Now, how can we say that?
どうしてそう言えるでしょうか
Well, let’s have a look together
マタイによる福音書の
24章に記されている
at the famous prophecy
that’s recorded in Matthew chapter 24
有名な預言をご一緒に見てみましょう
—Matthew 24:3.
マタイ 24:3です
Remember, the apostles
at this particular time
ご存じのように この時 使徒たちは
were asking Jesus a very important question.
とても大切な点をイエスに尋ねています
It’s at the second part of verse 3.
3節の後半部分をご覧ください
It says they asked: “Tell us,
こう尋ねています 「教えてください
“when will these things be,
そのようなことはいつあるのでしょうか
“and what will be the sign of your presence
あなたの臨在と体制の
終結のしるしは何ですか」
and of the conclusion
of the system of things?”
聖書を学んできた皆さんは
Now, you remember, no doubt
from your previous studies of the Bible,
よくご存じだと思いますが
how Jesus then went on to list
many events that would occur
イエスはこの後 終わりの時代に起きる
幾つもの出来事を挙げていきます
during the last days.
He mentioned wars;
戦争があること 地震が起きること
he mentioned earthquakes;
he mentioned famines
食糧不足やいろいろな流行病が
生じることを述べました
and all sorts of pestilences.
確かに最近そうしたことが起きています
Truly we have seen those things happen
in recent times.
それに加えて マタイ 24:14は
In addition to all of that, Matthew 24:14
「王国の良い知らせ」を伝える
必要があることを述べています
mentioned the need to preach
the “good news of the Kingdom.”
But there could be some who
perhaps may doubt a little
こうした話を聞くと
こんなふうに感じる人も
いるかもしれません
and say: ‘Well, there’s been wars
all through time.
「でも 戦争はいつの時代にもあった
地震も終わりの時代だけじゃなくて
ほかの時代にも起きている
‘There’s been earthquakes at other times,
not just in the last days,
食糧不足もそうだ
‘and food shortages.
どうして今がその時だと
確信できるんだろうか
‘So why can we be so sure
‘that this is the time
‘when we know that Jesus
will soon bring about
イエスが悪いことを終わらせる時が
本当に近いと
どうして言えるんだろうか」
an end to wickedness?’
Well, let’s use an illustration.
例えで考えてみましょう
Most of us are familiar
with using a computer.
たいていの方は
コンピューターを使われるでしょう
Now, when you sit at your computer,
コンピューターの前に座って
what’s the first thing that you need to do
after you’ve turned it on?
電源を入れてから まず
何をする必要がありますか
Usually, you have to type in a password,
don’t you?
普通はパスワードを入れる
必要がありますね
And you have to get it right.
数字や文字を間違いなく全て
その通りに打ち込まなければなりません
You have to put in all those numbers
and letters that are required.
Otherwise, you won’t be able
to start working on the computer.
そうしないとコンピューターを
使うことができません
Now, these days people are very concerned
最近では強力なパスワードを
使う大切さが強調されます
about having strong passwords.
What do you think if you had a password
では 24の文字と数字から成る
パスワードを使っているとしましょう
that had 24 different letters and numbers?
強力なパスワードです
That’s a very strong password,
and it would be very difficult for someone
誰かがあなたのコンピューターの
ロックを解除しようとして
to just randomly try and find out
what those numbers are
ただ適当に文字や数字を打ち込んでも
まず当たらないでしょう
and unlock your computer.
Well, how does that relate
to the sign that Jesus gave?
これがイエスの話したしるしと
どう関係するのでしょうか
Notice that if you look back at Matthew 24:3,
マタイ 24:3に戻りましょう
ここの「しるし」は
the question was not
the “signs” of your presence
原語で複数形ではなく
単数形になっています
but the “sign.”
Just like a password—one sign.
このしるしはパスワードのようです
But then that sign
has many different features
全体として1つですが
幾つもの要素から成っています
—in fact, at least 24 different features.
しるしには少なくとも
24の要素があります
So even though there have been wars
in the past,
それで戦争は以前にもありましたが
this is the time when we see
今はしるしの全ての要素が
一度に現れている時です
all those features
coming together at one time.
And in that way, we could say
it opens the fulfillment
ですから聖書預言が
実現していると言えるのです
of Bible prophecy.
Yes, as we look around us,
as we listen to the news each day,
周りを見て毎日ニュースを聞いていると
we can see
that there is a definite fulfillment
イエスの言ったことがまさに
実現していることが分かります
of what Jesus said.
Truly, the end is close.
本当に終わりは近いのです
It’s just like a jigsaw puzzle,
to use another illustration.
ジグソーパズルの例えも
考えてみましょう
When you have all the pieces
of a jigsaw puzzle
ピース1つでは何の絵か分かりませんが
and you start to put them all together,
ピースをはめていくと
eventually when all the pieces are in place,
最終的に全てのピースが合わさって
1つの絵が出来上がります
the picture is clear, isn’t it?
And that’s exactly how we should feel
まさに同じことをイエスの話した
預言についても言うことができます
about the prophecy that Jesus gave.
間もなく もう間もなく
Soon, very soon,
he is going to step in and take action.
イエスは行動を起こします
But, of course, sometimes we may feel,
でもこう感じることがありますか
‘Yes, we’ve known about this
for quite some time.’
「このことはかなり前から知っている」
And it means that we’ve had to wait
a long time.
つまり 長い間
待ってきたということです
But that doesn’t negate the fact
でもだからといって
終わりの時代である証拠が
that the evidence of the last days is here.
否定されるわけではありません
Perhaps we could illustrate it this way:
こんな例えで考えられます
Most of us have gone to an airport
多くの方が 海外や別の地域から
来る友達を迎えに
to meet someone
who’s coming maybe from overseas
飛行場に行ったことがあるでしょう
or another part of the country.
Now, since 9/11,
it’s very hard to go to an airport
たいていの飛行場では
安全上の理由から
滑走路のそばに行って
and actually stand on the side of the runway
and see the plane land.
飛行機の動きを見ることはできません
Usually, what happens?
普通どうしますか
Once you get to the airport, you’re allowed
to go into a large room with other people,
空港に着いたら ほかの人たちと
到着ロビーに行って
電光掲示板を見ることができます
and all you see are monitors on the wall.
Now, what may the monitors say?
掲示板には何が表示されますか
Well, you see, it says there
that the flight has left.
飛行機が離陸したことが示されます
Then later, maybe the monitor says
the flight is on time.
その後 定刻通りと
表示されるかもしれません
Then it says the flight has landed.
それから着陸の表示が出ます
次に地上走行中と出ます
Then it says the flight is taxiing.
そして 手荷物引き渡し中と出て
Then it says it’s at the gate.
Well, now you start to get really excited,
don’t you?
もうすぐだと期待が高まります
飛行機も見えていませんし
And yet you haven’t seen the plane,
and you haven’t seen your friend yet.
友達もまだ見えていません
でも 電光掲示板の表示から
But you can see from the indications
もうすぐ友達に会える
ということが分かるのです
of what you see on the monitor
that it must be close.
And then all of a sudden, the doors open
and people start to come out.
それから 突然ドアが開いて
乗客が出てきます
Well, now you’re really excited
because you know,
待っていた友達に会えると思うと
本当にうれしくなります
yes, you’re going to meet your friend.
Well, that is similar
to how we can view the last days.
終わりの時代についても
同じ見方をすることができます
There has been a lot of things happening
that we don’t actually see.
私たちに見えない所で
多くのことが起きています
But we see the indications
of what’s happened.
私たちはその結果を見ています
And we know that very soon
間もなく イエスと天使と
選ばれた14万4000人が
Jesus, the angels, and the 144,000
will take steps to remove this old world
今の世界を除き去って
and then take further steps
平和の回復のために
さらに行動を取ります
toward the restoration of peace.
Isn’t that a beautiful promise?
素晴らしい希望ですね
そうすると 3つ目の点を
考えたくなります
So naturally, that takes us
to the third question:
How will universal peace be restored?
どのように再び全てが平和になるかです
What will Jesus need to do?
イエスは何をしますか
大まかに言って 2つのことを
する必要があります
Basically, we could say
there are two actions required.
One is to remove Satan
1つは サタンと平和を妨げる者を
取り除くことです
and the peace disturbers.
その後に行うもう1つのことは
And then the second action
サタンが行った悪いこと
全ての影響をなくすことです
is to undo all the evil that Satan has done.
You see, we don’t want a Band-Aid solution
—do we?—
私たちは ひどい傷があるのに
where you’re just hiding something
that’s very serious
バンドエイドを貼ってただ隠すような
解決策を望んではいません
by putting a Band-Aid over it.
So not only does Jesus need to take away
イエスは平和を乱す者たちを
取り除く必要があるだけでなく
those that are disrupting the peace,
but he also has to take steps
人類を癒やし 地球全体を癒やし
to heal mankind and to heal the earth
悪魔が悪いことを行って駄目にした
全てのものを元通りにするためにも
so that all the evil, the bad things
that Satan has done,
行動する必要があります
will be overturned.
では この2つのことについて
少し考えましょう
So let’s think about those two actions
for a moment.
1つ目は平和を妨げる者たちを
取り除くことでしたね
Remember, the first one
is to remove the peace disturbers.
それには何が含まれるでしょうか
What steps are involved with that?
Remember, this is a progressive action.
これは段階的に行われることです
If we take our Bibles
and turn to the book of Revelation,
どうぞ 聖書の「啓示」の書を
お開きください
we’ll see there are several things
mentioned here that help us to see
そこに記されている幾つかの点を見ると
平和を妨げる者たちを取り除くために
how progressively Jesus
has and will bring about
イエスが段階的に
どんなことをしてきたか
this removal of peace disturbers.
この先どんなことをするかが分かります
If you turn with me, please,
to Revelation chapter 12,
ご一緒に啓示 12章を開いて
9節を読みましょう
let’s read together verse 9
—Revelation 12.
啓示 12章と聞くと きっと皆さんは
Now, immediately, no doubt you remember
王国について述べられていることを
思い出されるでしょう
that Revelation 12
is talking about the time
when Jesus’ government, his Kingdom,
was established in the heavens.
イエスが治めるその王国が
天で設立されたのは
1914年です
That was in 1914.
In verse 9, it mentions
その後にどんなことが
起きたかを述べている
what happened shortly after that time.
9節に注目しましょう
読みます
Let’s read it:
“So down the great dragon was hurled,
「こうして 大きな竜は投げ落とされた
“the original serpent,
the one called Devil and Satan,
あの初めの蛇で 悪魔サタンと呼ばれ
全世界を惑わしている者である
“who is misleading
the entire inhabited earth;
彼は地に投げ落とされ
“he was hurled down to the earth,
邪悪な天使たちも共に投げ落とされた」
and his angels were hurled down with him.”
Did you notice that word
that came up several times
どんな言葉が繰り返されていましたか
「投げ落とされ」るです
—“hurled” down?
イエスはサタンの所に行って
こう言ったりはしませんでした
You see, Jesus didn’t go and say to Satan:
‘Well, look, if you don’t mind,
「もしよろしければ 地球に
移動していただきたいのですが
‘we’d like you to relocate to the earth.
いつでも大丈夫です」
Whenever you’re ready.’
そうではなく 投げ落としました
No, Satan was hurled down.
And what confidence that gives us!
信仰が強められますね
That means that Jesus has the power
イエスにはサタンを天から除き去る
力があるということだからです
to be able to remove Satan from the heavens.
That gives us some idea
of what’s going to happen in the future
地球が将来どうなるかについて
安心感を抱けます
with regard to the earth.
Of course, now we’re living in a time
when Satan and his demons
とはいえ 今はサタンと邪悪な
天使たちが地球の近辺にいて
are here in the vicinity of the earth,
いろいろな問題を引き起こしています
and they are causing so much trouble.
So, what’s another step that Jesus will take
それで イエスは平和を
乱す者たちを除き去るために
in removing those who disrupt the peace?
次にどんな行動を取るでしょうか
Well, let’s look at another chapter
in the same book,
「啓示」の書の別の章に
注意を向けましょう
Revelation chapter 19
19章です
—Revelation chapter 19.
ここでは啓示 19:19-21を
お読みしたいと思います
And we’re going to read starting at verse 19
right through to 21.
We might mention before we start reading it
読む前に少し説明して
おきたいと思いますが
that here it describes
political organizations, kings,
ここでは 政治組織 王たち
イエスとエホバ神に敵対する
者たちのことが描かれています
and those who oppose
Jesus and Jehovah God.
And in a symbolic way,
it refers to these as beasts,
そして平和を乱してきた政治組織が
ここでは象徴的に
野獣と述べられています
as organizations,
that have disrupted the peace.
Let’s see what happens to them:
では 見てみましょう
“And I saw the wild beast
and the kings of the earth and their armies
「さらに見ると 野獣と
地上の王たちとその軍勢が
“gathered together to wage war
against the one seated on the horse
馬に乗っている方
［つまり イエス・キリスト］と
“and against his army
[now, that one is Jesus Christ].
その軍勢に対して戦うために
集まっていた
“And the wild beast was caught,
そして 野獣は捕らわれ
野獣の前で奇跡を行った
偽預言者も捕らわれた
“and along with it the false prophet
“that performed in front of it the signs
偽預言者は野獣の印を受けた者たちと
野獣の像を崇拝する者たちを
“with which he misled those who received
the mark of the wild beast
奇跡によって惑わしていたのである
“and those who worship its image.
野獣も偽預言者も生きたまま
“While still alive,
“they both were hurled into the fiery lake
硫黄が燃える火の湖に投げ込まれた」
that burns with sulfur.”
いかがでしたか
So, what happens
to these political organizations
エホバとイエスに反対する
政治組織はどうなりますか
in opposition to Jehovah and Jesus?
滅ぼされます そして ここでも
Again, we see the word
“hurled” down into destruction.
「投げ込まれた」とありました
And what about the rest of mankind
イエスの統治に反対する
ほかの人たちについてはどうでしょうか
that opposes Jesus’ rule?
Well, let’s look at verse 21.
21節を読みましょう
What does it say?
こうあります 「ほかの者たちは
“But the rest were killed off
“with the long sword
that proceeded out of the mouth
馬に乗っている方の口から
出ている長い剣で殺された
“of the one seated on the horse.
And all the birds
were filled with their flesh.”
全ての鳥が彼らの肉で満腹になった」
Now, that’s a very interesting comment,
isn’t it?
これはとても興味深い聖句ですね
It helps us to see here
この聖句から
that all those who oppose Jesus
イエスに反対する人たちは皆
ハルマゲドンの戦いの時に
滅ぼされるということが分かります
will be destroyed
in the battle of Armageddon.
So that’s another step
これが全てを平和にするために
必要な別の行動です
in getting ready for universal peace.
First of all, Satan is cast out of heaven.
まず サタンが天から投げ落とされます
And then secondly, at Armageddon,
そして次に イエスに逆らい
all those humans who rebelled against Jesus
イエスの統治を退ける全ての人たちが
and reject his rule
ハルマゲドンの戦いで皆
滅ぼされることになります
will be taken away, destroyed.
But there’s something else too.
それだけではありません
Let’s look at chapter 20 of Revelation
啓示 20章を見てみましょう
20:1-3を読みます
—chapter 20 and verses 1-3:
“And I saw an angel coming down
out of heaven with the key of the abyss
「私がさらに見ていると
底知れぬ深みの鍵と大きな鎖を持った
天使が天から下ってきた
“and a great chain in his hand.
“He seized the dragon, the original serpent,
その天使は あの初めの蛇である竜
悪魔サタンを捕らえて
“who is the Devil and Satan,
1000年間動けないように縛った
“and bound him for 1,000 years.
“And he [notice the word again]
hurled him into the abyss
そして竜を底知れぬ深みに投げ込み
［ここでもまた出てきました］
“and shut it and sealed it over him,
そこを閉じて封印し
1000年が終わるまで
“so that he would not mislead
the nations anymore
竜がもはや人々を惑わさないようにした
“until the 1,000 years were ended.
その後 竜はしばらくの間
解放されることになる」
After this he must be released
for a little while.”
What do we notice from this description?
この記述から何が分かるでしょうか
You see, gradually, in a progressive manner,
ここまで イエスが段階的な仕方で
Jesus will eradicate and remove
平和を乱す者たちを打ち負かし
those who disrupt peace.
取り除くことを考えてきました
So Satan and his demons
are cast down to the earth.
サタンと邪悪な天使たちが
地に投げ落とされました
At the battle of Armageddon,
those who rebelled will be destroyed.
反逆する者たちがハルマゲドンの
戦いで滅ぼされます
それから サタンが底知れぬ深みという
象徴的な牢獄に邪悪な天使たちと共に
And then Satan will be put
in a symbolic prison, in this abyss,
for 1,000 years along with his demons.
1000年間閉じ込められます
ここまでがイエスが行う
必要がある1つ目のこと
So that’s the first action
that Jesus needs to do
問題を起こす者たちを取り除くことです
—to get rid of these troublemakers.
That opens up the way
for what the Bible refers to
こうして聖書の中で約束されている
イエス・キリストと
共同統治者たちによる
as the Thousand Year Reign of Jesus Christ
王国の千年統治が始まることになります
with his Kingdom and corulers.
What is going to happen
千年統治の期間中に
during that Thousand Year Reign?
どんなことが起きるのでしょうか
Remember we said that it’s not
a Band-Aid-type solution, is it?
それはバンドエイドのような
解決策ではないとお話ししましたね
He will need to help
イエスが人類と地球を癒やすために
行動してくださいます
mankind and the earth to heal.
Notice, please, how this is described for us
すでに読んだ聖句に そのことが
どう表現されていたかに注目しましょう
in a scripture that we’ve already read.
もう一度 ヨハネ第一 3:8を
お開きください
Let’s turn to it again—1 John 3:8.
Remember in the beginning of that verse,
その聖句の前半に
全てが平和な状態がそもそもどのように
乱されたかが書かれていました
that’s where it told us how universal peace
was disrupted in the beginning,
at the time when that angel
天使が悪魔になって罪を
犯し始めた時のことです
became the Devil and started sinning.
But notice what it says
in the second part of this verse:
では この聖句の後半部分を
お読みします
“For this purpose
「神の子が現れたのは
“the Son of God was made manifest,
[to do what?]
［何をするためとありますか］
悪魔の行いを終わらせるため
to break up [or to destroy]
the works of the Devil.”
［つまり 滅ぼすため］です」
Isn’t that an amazing concept?
すごいことをしますね
Jesus not only removes
those who disrupt peace,
イエスは平和を乱す者たちを
除き去るだけでなく
but he will “break up
the works of the Devil,”
「悪魔の行いを終わらせ」ます
悪魔が地球を支配して何千年もの間に
行ってきたことを終わらせるのです
the things that he’s done
over these thousands of years
that he’s been ruling this earth.
That means all the evil,
これは悪も苦しみも死も
all the suffering, death,
全てなくなるということです
all of that will be taken away.
Mankind will be gradually healed.
人類は徐々に癒やされます
Now, Jesus started to break up
the works of the Devil
イエスが悪魔の行いを
終わらせることを始めたのは
自分の命を贖いとして差し出した時です
when he willingly gave his life as a ransom.
So even now we have the opportunity
それで今でも エホバとの平和
ほかの人との平和を
ある程度得ることができます
to gain a measure of peace
with Jehovah and with others.
We can ask Jehovah for forgiveness
贖いの犠牲に基づいてエホバに
許しを求めることができます
based on the ransom sacrifice.
But during the Thousand Year Reign,
でも千年統治の間
there will be further things
that Jesus will accomplish.
イエスはもっと多くのことを
してくださいます
Notice these three aspects:
簡単に3つの点を挙げましょう
イエスは害となるもの
全てを拭い去ります
He will undo all harm.
Now, that includes sickness, war,
病気 戦争 食糧不足など
全ての問題をなくし
disease, famine, all these problems;
全てを元の良い状態に戻します
all the harm will be undone.
He will also undo death
イエスは死も拭い去り
by resurrecting those who have died.
亡くなった人たちを復活させます
And he will also undo sin
そして 罪も拭い去り
by helping mankind to grow to perfection.
人間が完全になるのを助けます
Isn’t that a beautiful promise,
素晴らしい約束ですね
undoing all these works of the Devil?
悪魔が駄目にしたものが
元通りになります
And then by the end of the thousand years,
そして 千年統治の終わりまでに
what will we see with regard to the earth?
地球はどんな状態になるでしょうか
It will be a paradise.
地球はパラダイスになります
まさにエホバが最初に考えておられた
通りの状態になるのです
It will be exactly
as Jehovah purposed it to be
in the beginning.
Yes, Jesus, by means of the Kingdom,
このようにしてイエスは王国によって
悪魔の行い全てを完全に終わらせます
will have completely broken up
the works of the Devil.
Now, is that the time then
では その時に再び全てが
平和な状態になるのでしょうか
when universal peace is restored?
いいえ まだそうはなりません
No, not quite yet.
Why not?
さらに必要なことがあります
Something else has to happen.
And we’re going to reread another scripture,
and that’s Romans 16.
別の聖句ももう一度読みましょう
ローマ 16章です
最初に読みましたね
Remember we referred to that
in the beginning.
Here we see a very interesting connection
どんな2つのことが関係付けられて
いるか注目しながら読みましょう
between two different things.
So that’s Romans 16:20:
ローマ 16:20
“For his part, the God who gives peace
「平和を与える神により
［次に注目です］
“[will do what?]
間もなくサタンは皆さんの
足の下で砕かれます」
will crush Satan under your feet shortly.”
Do we see the connection here?
お分かりになったでしょうか
Universal peace is connected
全ての平和が 悪魔サタンが
砕かれることと関係付けられています
with the crushing of Satan the Devil.
So universal peace can only be restored
つまり サタンが滅ぼされて初めて
再び全てが平和になるのです
after Satan has been destroyed.
Now, what events will occur
leading up to Satan’s destruction?
サタンが滅ぼされる前に
どんなことが起きるでしょうか
Well, remember,
as we read already in Revelation,
先ほどの啓示の聖句にあったように
Satan is going to be allowed
サタンは底知れぬ深みという
象徴的な牢獄から解放され
to be released from that prison
(the symbolic prison),
その時地上に生活している人たちを
惑わすことをしばらくの間許されます
and he’ll have an opportunity
to try to mislead
people who are living on the earth
at that time.
Those who join Satan
will be destroyed forever.
サタンの側に付く人たちは
永遠に滅ぼされます
Then Satan will be permanently destroyed.
そして サタンも永遠に滅ぼされます
But what will happen to those perfect persons
では エホバに忠実であることを示す
完全な人たちはどうなるでしょうか
who prove faithful to Jehovah?
Let’s see what the Bible says
聖書が何と述べているか
if we turn to the book of Romans,
ローマ 8章を開いて読みましょう
Romans 8:21
ローマ 8:21です
—Romans 8:21:
8:21
“That the creation itself
「創造物も
“will also be set free
from enslavement to corruption
腐敗への奴隷状態から自由にされ
神の子供の輝かしい自由を
得るという希望です」
“and have the glorious freedom
of the children of God.”
What does that really mean?
どういうことでしょうか
It means that at that point,
ここで言っているのは その時
全ての人がエホバの大きな家族の
一員になるということです
everyone will become part
of Jehovah’s universal family.
All intelligent creatures
in heaven and on earth
1つの家族として結ばれた
天と地の全ての者たちが
will be united as one family
唯一の真の神であるエホバへの
清い崇拝を一致して行います
in the pure worship
of the one true God, Jehovah.
What a beautiful time that will be!
何と素晴らしい時でしょう
最後に考えるのは
But what further blessings
are involved with this process
全ての平和が段階的に達成される間に
得られる祝福です
of gradually bringing universal peace?
Well, during the Thousand Year Reign
of Jesus,
イエスの千年統治の間に
素晴らしい祝福がもたらされます
there’s going to be wonderful blessings.
Those who are obedient
to Jehovah and Jesus
エホバとイエスに従順に従う人たちは
will experience the things
that were described
聖書の詩編 72編に
描かれている事柄を経験します
in the Bible book of Psalms, in Psalm 72.
Let’s turn there together
詩編 72編をご一緒に開きましょう
—Psalm 72.
And here we see portrayed
千年統治について
some very interesting prophetic statements
その時に実現するとても興味深い
預言の言葉が記されています
about the Thousand Year Reign.
You’ll notice at the beginning,
it says regarding Solomon—
表題に 「ソロモンについて」
とあります
So although initially
this was referring to an extent
この預言の言葉はソロモンの時代に
ある程度実現しましたが
with regard to Solomon,
Jesus mentioned
that he’s greater than Solomon.
イエスはソロモンより偉大な方です
So this has a prophetic application
それで この預言はイエスの
千年統治にも当てはまります
to the Thousand Year Reign.
Let’s see what it says about peace.
平和について何と述べているでしょうか
Starting in verse 1,
1節から4節まで読みます
we’ll go through to verse 4:
“O God, give your judgments to the king,
「神よ どのように裁くかを
王に教えてください
“and endow the son of the king
with your righteousness.
王の子があなたの正しさに
倣えますように
“May he plead the cause of your people
with righteousness,
王があなたの民の訴えを正しく取り上げ
立場が低い人を公正に扱いますように
“and of your lowly ones with justice.
“May the mountains bring peace to the people,
山が平和を 丘が正義を
民にもたらしますように
“and may the hills bring righteousness.
王が 民の中の立場が低い人を守り
“Let him defend the lowly among the people,
貧しい人の子たちを救い
“let him save the sons of the poor,
だまし取る人を打ち倒しますように」
and let him crush the defrauder.”
What a beautiful description
千年統治の間に起きることが
of what will happen
in the Thousand Year Reign!
本当に美しく描かれています
サタンの支配する世界で
ひどい目に遭っていた
Yes, all those under Satan’s rule
who were lowly, beaten up, disadvantaged
立場の低い恵まれない人たちは皆
—all these will experience relief
イエス・キリストの正しい統治の下で
because of the righteous rule
of Jesus Christ.
安心して暮らすことができます
少し進んで12節から
14節を見ましょう
Let’s go down a little further
to verses 12 through 14.
It tells us a little more
about what Jesus will accomplish.
イエスの行うことが
さらに書かれています
Starting in verse 12, we’re told:
12節からお読みします
「王は 助けを求めて叫ぶ
貧しい人を救い出す
“For he will rescue the poor
who cry for help,
“also the lowly one
and whoever has no helper.
立場が低い人や誰にも
助けてもらえない人も
“He will have pity on the lowly and the poor,
立場が低い人や貧しい人を哀れに思い
“and the lives of the poor he will save.
貧しい人の命を救う
“From oppression and from violence
he will rescue them,
虐げと暴力からその人たちを助け出す
“[and notice
this very interesting expression]
［次の興味深い表現に
注目してください］
and their blood will be
precious in his eyes.”
彼らの血は王の目に貴いものとなる」
What does that mean?
ここの「彼らの血は王の目に貴い」
とはどういう意味でしょうか
“Their blood will be precious in his eyes.”
In the Bible, usually the word “blood”
聖書で 「血」はよく命と
関連付けられますね
is associated with life, isn’t it?
So it’s saying that each person’s life
それで 一人一人の命が
イエス・キリストにとって
貴いということです
will be precious to Jesus Christ.
What a beautiful description
千年統治の間に起きる本当に
素晴らしいことが予告されています
of what will happen
during the Thousand Year Reign!
Then if we go back a little to verse 5,
それではここで5節に戻って
we’ll notice that this part of the psalm
helps us to see
その時に平和がどれほど
広く行き渡るかを
詩編のこの部分から見てみましょう
how widespread peace will be at that point.
印象的な表現が使われています
It uses very picturesque language.
Notice there in verse 5, it says:
5節から読みましょう
“They will fear you
as long as there is a sun
「民はあなたを畏れる
太陽がある限り
“[well, we know the sun continues on,
so they’ll continue to fear him]
［太陽はいつまでもあるので
いつまでもということです］
“and as long as the moon remains,
月がある限りずっと
“for generation after generation.
何代にもわたって
“He will be like the rain
that falls on the mown grass,
王は刈られた草地に降る雨のようになる
“like showers of rain that water the earth.
地面を潤す豊かな雨のように
“In his days the righteous will flourish,
王が治める間
正しい人たちは幸せに暮らし
“and peace will abound
until the moon is no more.
平和が行き渡る
月がなくなる時までも
“He will have subjects from sea to sea
王の統治は海から海に及ぶ
and from the River to the ends of the earth.”
川から地の果てにまで」
Yes, what a beautiful description
ここで イエスの王国の下で
of the peaceful arrangements
that will prevail
平和が地球に広く行き渡る
千年統治の様子が
during the Thousand Year Reign
of Jesus’ Kingdom!
美しく描かれています
But then the thousand years finishes.
そして 千年統治が終わります
What can we expect when that reign ends?
その時どんなことが起きるのでしょうか
I’m sure you’re going to enjoy
our consideration
ここでぜひじっくり考えたい
とても大切な聖句があります
of a very special part of the Scriptures
—1 Corinthians chapter 15.
コリント第一 15章です
どうぞお開きください
Please turn there with me,
and we’re going to go through
and look at what these verses tell us
これから一緒に考える聖句には
千年統治が終わった後に
about after the end
of the Thousand Year Reign.
どんなことが起こるかが書かれています
これから読むのは
The section of Scripture
we’re going to consider
コリント第一 15:24-28
の部分です
is 1 Corinthians chapter 15,
verses 24-28.
Starting in verse 24, we’re told:
24節からお読みします
“Next, the end,
「次いで 終わりとなります
その時 キリストは父である神に
王国を渡します
“when he hands over the Kingdom
to his God and Father,
“when he has brought to nothing
その時までに キリストは全ての政府
“all government and all authority and power.
また全ての権威と力を除き去っています
“For he must rule as king
神がキリストに全ての敵を
踏みつけさせるまで
“until God has put
all enemies under his feet.
キリストは王として治めるのです
“And the last enemy, death,
そして最後の敵である
死が除き去られます
“is to be brought to nothing.
神は『彼を全てのものの
上に立たせた』からです
“For God ‘subjected all things
under his feet.’
ここで 『全てのもの』が
服従するようになったと
“But when he says
that ‘all things have been subjected,’
述べられているとはいえ
その中に 全てのものを
キリストに服従させた方が
“it is evident that this does not include
“the One who subjected all things to him.
含まれていないのは明らかです
“But when all things
will have been subjected to him,
全てのものがキリストに
服従させられた後
“then the Son himself
will also subject himself
神の子自身も 全てのものを自分に
服従させた方に服従します
“to the One who subjected all things to him,
that God may be all things to everyone.”
こうして 誰にとっても
神が全てになるのです」
What do these verses tell us
about the end of the Thousand Year Reign?
千年統治の終わりについて
何が分かりますか
Well, let’s go back to verse 24.
24節に戻りましょう
There it says: “Next, the end . . .”
「次いで 終わりとなります」
とあります
Now, this “end” mentioned here
is not Armageddon.
この「終わり」はハルマゲドンの
ことではありません
This is the end of the Thousand Year Reign.
それは千年統治の終わりのことです
At the end of the Thousand Year Reign,
千年統治が終わる時に
それ以外にも終わるものが
幾つかあります
there are some other things too
that will have finished.
That means for a start,
1つとして 王国のやるべきことは
終わっています
the end of the Kingdom arrangement.
There will also be an end to sin,
そして 罪もなくなっています
which means that mankind will no longer need
人類はもはや 贖いも仲介者も
祭司も必要としません
the ransom or a mediator or priesthood.
And then in verse 26, notice it says:
26節にはこう書かれていました
“The last enemy, death,
is to be brought to nothing.”
「最後の敵である死が除き去られます」
In other words, the graves will be empty.
つまり 墓は空になって
Those who have experienced the Adamic death
アダムの罪の結果として死んだ人たちは
復活しています
will have been brought back.
人類は皆 アダムに起因する
罪から解放されて
Mankind will all attain to perfection
with the end of sin
—Adamic sin.
完全になっています
So at that point in time,
それでその時点で
something very, very special happens.
とてもとても特別なことが起きます
何でしょうか
What is it?
Well, let’s go back
to the beginning of our discussion
考えている4つの点の最初の部分で
エデンの園でどんな問題が
起きたかについてお話ししました
when we talked about the problems
that occurred in the garden of Eden.
Remember, Satan the Devil raised some issues
その時 悪魔サタンが問題を提起して
that resulted in a symbolic court case
いわば裁判が始まり
エホバのお名前が神聖なもの
とされる必要が生じました
that involves the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name.
Yes, Satan had claimed
that Jehovah is a liar,
サタンは 「エホバはうそつきだ
エホバの統治は愛による
ものではない」と主張し
that he doesn’t rule mankind out of love,
後に 「エホバに仕える者など
いるのか」という疑問を投げ掛けました
and he even raised the question later
about who would actually serve Jehovah.
So this issue has continued on
この問題 エホバの名の
神聖さを巡る問題は
—the issue of the sanctification
of Jehovah’s name—right down through history.
現代に至るまで続いています
And over and over again,
Jehovah’s name has been sanctified.
エホバのお名前は何度も
神聖なものとされてきました
His reputation has been vindicated.
その評判への疑いは晴らされてきました
We can see that he’s a loving God,
エホバが あのひどいサタンとは違って
愛のある方であることは明らかです
unlike Satan
—such a horrible person.
But Jehovah has stood out
as being a loving heavenly Father.
エホバは本当に愛のある
天のお父さんではないでしょうか
それで 将来のその時点で
So now at this point in time,
全ての者が関わる裁判が
決着を見ることになります
we can say the universal court case
comes to a conclusion.
The issue is settled—the verdict is given.
問題は解決され 判決が下ります
どのようにでしょうか
In what way?
Well, Jesus has just finished ruling mankind
for a thousand years,
イエスは14万4000人と共に
1000年間人類を
統治し終えたところです
along with the 144,000
that have made the earth a paradise.
地球をパラダイスにしました
人類は罪から自由にされ
完全になっています
Mankind is now no longer sinners;
they’re perfect.
悪いことは全てなくなりました
All the problems have been healed.
So at this point in time, what does Jesus do?
では この時点でイエスは
どうするでしょうか
Does he follow the example of Satan
and say: ‘Well, you know,
サタンに倣ってこう言うでしょうか
「まあ 私たちこの1000年間
かなりいい仕事をしてきましたよね
‘I think we did a very, very good job
for this thousand years.
‘So let’s just keep everything in place,
全部このままにして 私たちが王国で
治め続けることにしましょう」
and we’ll keep on ruling in the Kingdom.’
No, we saw what he does.
イエスはそんなことはしません
At that point in time,
まさにその時点で
there’s a marvelous answer in this court case
この裁判は素晴らしい結末を迎えます
イエス・キリストは 王国を
父であるエホバに返します
because Jesus hands over
the Kingdom back to his Father.
He submits to Jehovah’s rule.
エホバの統治に従うのです
And it’s just as if Jehovah
エホバにとって愛する子イエスから
こう言われているかのようです
is told by his loving Son, Jesus:
“You were right all along.
「あなたはずっと正しい方でした
“This whole thing
それなのに あなたにとってあまりに
不当なことがずっと続いてきました
“has been a terrible travesty of justice.
サタンはどうしようもない
うそつきです」
Satan is a despicable liar.”
And all mankind, including Jesus
こうして全ての人もイエスも
14万4000人も
and the 144,000,
submit themselves to Jehovah’s rulership.
エホバの統治に従います
Yes, the end of the universal issue.
エデンの園で提起された
問題が終わります
Jehovah will then rule directly
over perfect mankind.
エホバが完全な人たちを
直接治めることになります
But is that the point in time
when universal peace is restored?
では その時点で再び全てが
平和な状態になるのでしょうか
No, remember, there are some other things
that need to occur.
いいえ まだ起きることがありましたね
すでに述べたように サタンが
象徴的な牢獄から解放され
We’ve already mentioned
that Satan will be released
from his symbolic prison.
しばらくの間 人々を惑わす
機会を与えられます
He’ll have an opportunity
to try and mislead some.
サタンの側に付く人に
And for those who side with him,
Jehovah morally and ethically
doesn’t have to wait any longer
エホバが猶予を与え
「別の裁判をしましょう」と言う
必要はもはやありません
and say: ‘Well, let’s have
another court case.’
No, they are executed immediately.
その人たちはすぐに滅ぼされます
ほかの人たちはどうなるのでしょうか
But what about the rest of mankind?
They become Jehovah’s sons and daughters.
エホバの息子また娘となります
They can talk to him directly
without the need of a mediator.
エホバと直接話せます
仲介者も要りません
And then names will be written permanently
in “the book of life.”
その人たちの名前は永遠に
「命の書」に記されます
They’ll be approved
to live forever in Paradise.
エホバに認められて楽園で
永遠に生きられます
So at this point, when we’re thinking
ではここで これから起きる
素晴らしいことについて考えながら
about all these beautiful things
that will occur,
let’s enjoy the final video
of our convention.
この大会の最後のビデオを見ましょう
千年統治とさらにその先の
祝福が描かれています
It highlights the blessings
of the Thousand Year Reign and beyond.
And also, we’re going to listen
この大会の最後にみんなで歌う
オリジナルソングのビデオです
to the original song that we will sing
at the conclusion of our program.
どうぞご覧ください
Like an island of calm
In dark stormy seas,
この世界がどんよりと暗く沈んでも
God’s people
are living in peace.
信仰の目には見える 明るい未来が
With our eyes of faith,
We see beyond the clouds
And know that the storm
soon will cease.
川を越えて山も越え その向こうまで
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
この地球の果てにまで 平和 満ちる
All creation will see
Peace at last.
ついに
When the new world is here,
All will be one
一つになる 天地が新しくなって
On earth
and in heaven above.
And the peace we’ll know
We’ve never known before—
誰もまだ見たことない 平和 訪れる
A world ruled
by justice and love.
川を越えて山も越え その向こうまで
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
この地球の果てにまで 平和 満ちる
All creation will see
Peace at last.
ついに
川を越えて山も越え その向こうまで
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
For all eternity.
この地球の果てにまで 平和 満ちる
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
All creation will see.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
川を越えて山も越え その向こうまで
For all eternity.
From the valleys below
To the mountaintops,
この地球の果てにまで 平和 満ちる
All creation will see
Peace at last,
ついに
Peace at last!
What a beautiful song!
美しい歌でした
And what beautiful images to encourage us!
励みを与える美しいビデオでした
So brothers and sisters, we’ve enjoyed
our convention program, haven’t we?
兄弟姉妹 この大会を本当に
楽しまれたのではないでしょうか
Let us be determined to keep pursuing peace,
ではこれからも平和をつくりましょう
偽物の平和ではなく 本物の平和です
not an imitation peace, but the real peace.
We can enjoy rich blessings now
今でも豊かな祝福を味わえます
by having a peaceful relationship
with Jehovah God,
エホバ神との平和な関係を
持つことによって
yes, trying to continue
to maintain peace with one another
ほかの人との平和な関係を
持ち続けることによって
内面の平和 穏やかな気持ちを
持つよう努力することによってです
and also attaining to this inner peace
—calmness and tranquility—
because we have friendship
with the God who gives us hope.
私たちの友達である神が
希望を与えてくださるからです
And that hope helps us to look to the future,
その希望によって将来に
目を向けることができ
even though we have difficulties now,
いま難しい状況にあるとしても
and we look forward to the time
最終的に再び全てが平和になる時を
楽しみに待つことができます
when universal peace is finally restored.
それまでの間 そして永遠に
But in the meantime, may the God of peace
平和の神が皆さん一人一人と
共にいてくださいますように
be with each one of you now and forever!
Thank you, Brother Jackson.
ありがとうございました
兄弟の話や大会全体を通して
Your talk and this entire convention
have strengthened our confidence
エホバの預言に対する
確信が強まりました
in Jehovah’s prophetic Word
and helped us to understand
how close we are to its fulfillment.
その実現がどれほど近いかも
分かりました
On behalf of the Governing Body
統治体 そして
and all the hardworking members
of our Bethel families
世界各地のベテルや翻訳事務所で
熱心に働く奉仕者たちを代表して
and translation offices around the world,
we thank you for watching
the 2022 convention program.
大会のプログラムを視聴して
くださったことを感謝します
We have deep appreciation and affection
皆さん一人一人を心から愛し
for each one of you,
大切に思っています
and it is our prayer
私たちはこれからもエホバが皆さんに
that Jehovah continue
to bless you with peace.
平和を与えてくださるよう祈っています
Let’s conclude by singing a song
では最後に
エホバが間もなく実現させる
that reflects the complete peace
that Jehovah will soon bring about.
完全な平和についての
歌を歌いましょう
Please join in singing
the original song
結びの話の中でも聞いた
“Peace at Last!”
「平和が満ちる時」という
オリジナルソングです
which we heard during the concluding talk.
After the song,
歌の後 それぞれの場所で
you may have your concluding prayer
at your individual locations.
祈りを捧げてください
Now we invite all to sing out along
with the Watchtower chorus
では ものみの塔コーラス隊と一緒に
「平和が満ちる時」を歌いましょう
“Peace at Last!”